Okay, male genital system pathology, so we're going to start with the penis.
The very first disorder is called hypospadias, and this is when the urethra opens on the
inferior surface of the penis.
The name tells you a lot about this disorder, hypo means low, so it's on the lower surface
of the penis, and it's due to failure of the urethral folds to close, that's particularly
high yield for examination purposes.
Let's go back and remind ourselves of a little bit of embryology.
Remember that you've got this genital tubercle here, which eventually is going to become
the glands of the penis or the glands of the clitoris, and then running beneath it, you've
got this sort of bulk of tissue called the urethral fold.
Now what happens is that as the penis grows out, so imagine that the penis is coming sort
of 3D, as it's coming up and out, this urethral fold is going to seal, it's going to zipper
up.
And as this zippers up, that then seals the inferior surface of the penis and closes the
urethra inside of the penis.
If you were looking at it in cross section like this, what you'd actually see is something
like this, with these two bumps, let's put an A and a B here, with these two bumps representing
A and B here.
And of course this is the urethra here.
And so these are going to seal as the glands up here, as this genital tubercle begins to
come up and out.
And so these should seal.
And if they don't seal, then you can imagine that you'd have a hole on the inferior surface
of the penis from which urine would come out, and that is called hypospadias.
So that's the first disorder.
Again it's important to know for examination purposes, failure of the urethral folds to close.
That's particularly high yield.
Now epispadias, epi means on top, and so when you have epispadias, you have an opening of
the urethra on the superior surface of the penis.
This particular disorder is very rare, much more rare than hypospadias, and in this case
you have an abnormal positioning of the genital tubercle.
So let's go back and remind ourselves that if the genital tubercle was here, and then you
had this urethral fold here, and this was going to go up and out, and then this was going
to get the zipper closed, imagine that instead of being up here, the genital tubercle is here.
Now as this grows sort of up and out, this gets dragged along the superior surface, and
so now you've got this abnormal opening on the superior surface of the penis.
And epi again, very straightforward, epi means on top, so it's going to be on the superior
surface.
And this would be due to abnormal positioning of the genital tubercle.
So that's a little bit of embryology, but again, examiners love to go after that because
that's a great way to test embryology.
It's also associated with something called bladder extrophy, and bladder extrophy is when
you have opening of the anterior wall of the abdomen at the lower portion above the bladder,
such that the bladder wall is also not formed properly, and you get complete exposure of the
bladder wall as well.
And that's called bladder extrophy.
The next disorder is condyloma.
You're well aware of condyloma from our discussions of the female genital tract, so you can also
get a condyloma on the male tract, and just as it would be on the female tract, it's due
to HPV 6 and 11.
And in the same way, whenever you have HPV infection, that's always characterized by
coelocytic change.
This is the exact same picture that I showed you in the female genital section, and basically
I was trying to show you these raisinoid-appearing nuclei, these raisin-appearing nuclei, which indicate
coelocytic change, and that's, again, a hallmark of HPV infection.
Lymphogranuloma venerium is a necrotizing granulomatous inflammation of the inguinal lymphatics and
the lymph nodes.
It's a sexually transmitted disease caused by chlamydia trachomatis, in particular serotypes
L1 to L3.
Let's just go back and remind ourselves that chlamydia is an obligate intracellular organism.
It's not hard to remember because the chlamys, which the word chlamydia comes from, the chlamys
is the name of the cloak that was worn by men in ancient Greece, and so it's as if these
bugs are cloaked by the cells in which they grow.
So anyway, chlamydia is an obligate intracellular organism because it can't make ATP.
It needs to steal ATP from the cell, so it can only grow inside another cell.
And that's important because when you think about the, when you think about how you're going
to make a diagnosis, you need to grow the bug in another cell, so you can grow it in tissue
culture of cells, or you can grow it in chick embryo cells, et cetera.
It enters mucosal surfaces, generally speaking chlamydia, enters mucosal surfaces as elementary
bodies, and then they replicate into something called reticulate bodies, which are then released
as more elementary bodies, which can then infect again.
And remember that chlamydia trachomatis is divided into several serotypes.
So there's A through C, which causes trachoma, there's D through K, which causes urogenital
infections and conjunctivitis, and then there's L1 through L3.
And L1 to L3, as we're talking about here, that causes lymphogranuloma venerium.
Now eventually what happens is that you eventually get healing with fibrosis, but you can get rectal
strictures, especially if there's perianal involvement.
Squamous cell carcinoma of the penis is a malignant proliferation of squamous cells of
the penile skin.
The risk factors are going to be the same standard risk factors, in particular high-risk HPV.
16, 18, 31, 33, those are your high-risk HPVs.
Two-thirds of squamous cell carcinoma of the penis is due to high-risk HPV.
There is also an association with lack of circumcision, and the idea here is that if the patient has
foreskin, that can act as anitis for the inflammation and irritation if it's not properly maintained.
And so improper maintenance of the foreskin becomes a risk factor.
Now there are some precursor lesions to squamous cell carcinoma that are high-yield for exams.
Now the first is called Bowen's disease, and the way this presents is in-situ carcinoma.
All right, so these are precursor lesions, so they're going to be in-situ carcinoma.
So you have in-situ carcinoma that presents as leukoplakia, or a white plaque on the shaft of the penis,
and that's called Bowen's disease, so you would do a biopsy, and you would see malignant cells
that have not yet invaded the basement membrane, and that histology is important as well.
Erythroplasia of Kuert.
This is where the patient has in-situ carcinoma, but instead of presenting as leukoplakia,
it presents as erythroplakia, hence the term erythroplasia.
And this will also, this would be present on the glands of the penis.
So erythroplasia on the glands of the penis, again, it's a precursor lesion to squamous cell carcinoma of the penis.
And the third would be something called boanoid papulosis.
Now, basically, it's called papulosis because you have little papules, and they tend to be reddish.
And it's called boanoid because, like Bowen's disease, there's in-situ carcinoma.
However, it's not true Bowen's disease, because in Bowen's disease, that in-situ carcinoma would invade.
However, this usually does not progress to invasion, so it's boanoid.
It's like Bowen, but it doesn't progress to invasion.
So again, boanoid papulosis, reddish papules on the skin of the penis.
So that concludes our discussion of penis, and the next topic will be testicle.